<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to a most pernicious and factious petition, framed against the Scots in Ireland: together with the vindication of a gentleman from the false aspertions of Major Robert Ormesby: as also some serious queries to be presented to the said Major in behalfe of the state.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1647</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A75408</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3322</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E407_17</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R19932</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99860784</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99860784</idno>
            <idno type="VID">160510</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A75408)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 160510)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 64:E407[17])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to a most pernicious and factious petition, framed against the Scots in Ireland: together with the vindication of a gentleman from the false aspertions of Major Robert Ormesby: as also some serious queries to be presented to the said Major in behalfe of the state.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed in the year. 1647.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Vindicated gentleman is John Cunningham. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "7ber [i.e. September] 17th".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Cunningham, John, --  Captain.</term>
               <term>Ormesby, Robert.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Ireland --  History --  1625-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Kayla Ondracek</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:160510:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER to a moſt pernicious and factious PETITION, framed againſt the <hi>SCOTS</hi> in <hi>IRELAND:</hi> Together with the Vindication of a Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tleman from the falſe Aſpertions of <hi>Major ROBERT ORMESBY:</hi> As alſo ſome ſerious QUERIES to be preſented To the ſaid Major in behalfe of the STATE.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed in the Year. 1647.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="part">
            <pb facs="tcp:160510:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:160510:2"/>
            <head>An Anſwer to the infamous and ſcanda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous Libel, preſented by way of Petition to the Right Honorable, Sir THOMAS FAIRFAX his Excellency, in the name of the Engliſh now a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout London inhabiting, having intereſt in the Barronies of Raphoe and Kilmacrennan in the County of Donnegall and Kingdome of Ireland.</head>
            <div type="petition">
               <head>The Petition is thus</head>
               <opener>Sheweth,</opener>
               <p>WHereas the Engliſh Gentry had the greateſt ſhare of the barronies of <hi>Raphoe</hi> and <hi>Kilmacrennan,</hi> and other Lands in the County of <hi>Donnegal,</hi> lying on that ſide of the Mountains, and were poſſeſſed of ſeveral Caſtles, hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes and places of ſtrength. So it is, That <hi>Sr. William Stewart,</hi> and <hi>Sr. Robert Stuart</hi> (upon the Rebellion) raiſing of the <hi>Scots</hi> Nation, two Regiments of foot, and two Troops of horſe, have quartered them in thoſe parts, and not ſuffering any but their own Nation to have Command in in their Regiments, have ſo oppreſſed the poor Engliſh by ſetling Garriſons amongſt them, quartering upon thoſe that live there, and abſolutely diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of all Engliſh mens Lands at their meer wil and pleaſure, that the poor Engliſh are quite undone, and likely to be utterly rooted out of thoſe parts, unleſs ſome timely proviſion be made to free thoſe poor ſouls, that yet re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main, from their heavy preſſures, and to Countenance the Engliſh to ſit down upon their own again. And <hi>Sr. William Stuart</hi> being now dead, It is the humble Requeſt of the Engliſh now in London, who have relation to thoſe parts, that advantage may be taken of this opportunity, to ſend o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſome deſerving Engliſh Gentleman, to Command the ſaid <hi>Sir William</hi> his Regiment of Foot and Troop of horſe, and to ſend with him 300. Engliſh which may render him conſiderable, and ſubdue all mutinous endeavours
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:160510:3"/>to oppoſe him; And that his head quarter may be at Liffer, which is a ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry fine Engliſh Plantation, a Corporation and a conſiderable place of ſtrength, within ten miles of <hi>Derry,</hi> and ſo very ready to ſecond the Engliſh there; And that the reſt of the Garriſons in thoſe parts may be made and comman<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded by him: That ſo the languiſhing and poor oppreſſed Engliſh may be put into ſome heart to live, and hope to be freed of their heavy preſſures, and enjoy their own. And whereas the ſaid <hi>Sir William Stuart</hi> was vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>admiral of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> it is deſired the ſame may be conferred upon the <hi>Lord Folliot,</hi> Governor of <hi>Derry,</hi> and the Governor for the time being.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="answer">
               <head>The Anſwer is as followeth.</head>
               <p>SAith, That upon the breaking out of the horrid Rebellion of <hi>Ireland,</hi> Commiſſions were granted to <hi>Sir William Stuart,</hi> and <hi>Sir Robert Stuart</hi> to raiſe their Regiments of Foot, and Troops of horſe, which being ſo raiſed were put into the eſtabliſhment and <hi>Parl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aments</hi> pay. And fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſaith, That every word and ſentence ſet forth in the Petition againſt the ſaid Collonels, their Regiments and Troops in oppreſſing the Engliſh, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>habiting in the aforeſaid places, either by ſetling of Garriſons, or diſpoſing of their Lands at their pleaſure, to the undoing of the Engliſh, or that they made uſe of their own Nation, not ſuffering any Engliſhman to have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand amongſt them, is altogether untruth, and a moſt wicked and Nation<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al aſperſion. For to anſwer the laſt, Firſt. There was not an Engliſhman in that Country that could wear a ſword, but was imployed either as an Officer or Souldier according to his quality. As may appear by the liſt of Collonels, Lieutenant Collonels, Majors, Captains, and other inferior Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers of the Engliſh Nation in thoſe parts; And to this hour none of that Nation in thoſe parts are without Imployment, except ſuch as retired and withdrew themſelves from bearing a ſhare, and oppoſing the common Cala<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity. 2. As for oppreſſing them by ſeſſing or laying Garriſons on the En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh; ſo much as was preſerved from fire with the hazard and loſs of many mens lives (who might have withdrawn themſelves as others did, who came here to England) It was afterwards divided equally by advice and conſent of the Inhabitants of the Country, as wel <hi>Engliſh</hi> as <hi>Scots,</hi> amongſt the <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Souldiers</hi> of the four Regiments lying in thoſe parts; As by a diviſion under their hands may appear, for preſervation of the <hi>Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> lives, which was nothing upon the matter for ſuch a multitude, toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the Inhabitants of the Country. If hungry bellies and deſperate neceſſity had not extorted both food and rayment from the Rebels, who
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:160510:3"/>formerly had robbed thoſe who were alive of both Nations. And as for thoſe Lands that were waſted by the Rebels, and recovered again by the Souldiers, which are now beginning in ſome few places to be poſſeſſed and inhabited, for the eaſe of thoſe few quarters that have born Souldiers theſe ſix years, and are now impoveriſhed, and almoſt reduced to a total deva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtation; It is no prejudice to the owners who live in England far from dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, that ſome trenches and houſes be ſet upon their land, to make them habitable, when the enemy ſhal be reduced and beaten out of the field; for what can men expect of waſte lands, when the land which was never de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed by the enemy pays no rent at all? The Souldiers being neceſſitated to provide bread in ſome place til the Parliaments great occaſions give them time to provide better for theſe Regiments in thoſe parts. For if the Soldiers ſhould have left the Country, when they got no Proviſions from the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament either for back or belly, then the occaſion of that ſcandalous Libel had bin taken away long ere now, and the Country poſſeſſed peaceably by the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> til the Parliament of <hi>England</hi> ſhould get leaſure to make a new Conqueſt of <hi>Ireland.</hi> But if thoſe Petitioners wil either provide bread for the ſaid Regiments, or be Inſtruments to move the Parliament to provide bread, which is a reaſonable deſire, they ſhal be preſently poſſeſſed of their reſpective Claims or holdings, whereof they were diſpoſſeſt by the Rebels. And whereas the Petitioners (who are named poor ſouls) deſire to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leived from the preſſures of the <hi>Scots,</hi> by taking advantage of the opportu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity of <hi>Sir William Stuarts</hi> death, by ſending over an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man to Command <hi>Sir William Stuarts</hi> Regiment and Troop, and three hundred <hi>Engliſh</hi> men with him to make him conſiderable, that he may more eaſily ſuppreſs the mutinous indeavours of thoſe that oppoſe him: As this deſire is pernicious and factious (favouring of much malice) ſo it is unneceſſary, In reſpect the Parliament of England hath ſetled the command in chief of that Regiment and of the three other Regiments in <hi>Lagan</hi> upon an Engliſh man of ſuch integrity and worth, as that he is above envie or exception, <hi>Sir Charls Coote,</hi> Lord Preſident of <hi>Counaught;</hi> who alſo hath a Commiſsion from the Parliament, Authorizing him to diſpoſe of the quarters and Gari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons of thoſe foure Regiments and Troops as he in his Judgement ſhall finde moſt advantagious for the ſervice.</p>
               <p>And as for ſending over 300. men to oppoſe mutionous endeavours, It is very well known, that mutinie hath been a ſtranger to us in thoſe parts hitherto, or any falling out amongſt our Officers, but like an entire wall cemented together with braſſe couplets, we have all of us been uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together, which with the goodneſs of our cauſe and the bleſſing of God
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:160510:4"/>hath made us hitherto, maugre all the malice and power of the <hi>Iriſh,</hi> unvan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſhable. And it is our deſire th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the Doctrine of Mutinee be never taught nor profeſſed amongſt us, ſince diſobedience is as the ſin of Witchcraft. Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vertheleſſe we concur with the Petitioners in this; That the three hundred <hi>Engliſh</hi> men be ſent over with convenient proviſions for their ſubſiſtance, otherwiſe a greater burthen will be added to thoſe former preſſures, and make the cry greater. And as for a Collonel to command the Regiment and Troope; we doubt not but Sir <hi>Charles Coot,</hi> Lord Preſident of <hi>Connaught,</hi> Commander in chief, hath ſuch confidence in Sir <hi>John Cunningham,</hi> Lieute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant Collonel to the Regiment; and Captain <hi>John Stewart,</hi> Lieutenant to the Troop, and ſuch proof of their faithfulneſſe and zeale to the ſervice, who have ſerved in their ſeverall places theſe ſix years without reproofe, the Lieu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenant Collonel, raiſing and arming his Company at his owne charge, and to this hour quartering them upon his owne Inheritance (together with an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>other Company of Collonel <hi>Mervins</hi> Regiment) and who is likewiſe enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in great ſummes for Proviſions for the Regiment, not as yet diſcharged by the Parliament.</p>
               <p>And likewiſe Major <hi>Arskin,</hi> whoſe eſtate in times of peace was worth 1000 <abbr>l</abbr>'<hi>per annum,</hi> ought to be conſidered. We ſay theſe men recommended by Sir <hi>Charles Coote,</hi> who have ſerved out their ſeverall Apprentice-ſhips, ought to be made Free-men, and no ſtranger placed over their heads, unleſſe ſomething can be proved againſt their faithfulneſſe to the Parliaments ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice; and they doubt not but the Parliament is ſo noble and generous to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards thoſe that have deſerved well, That now when they cannot well re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward them for their great ſervices, they will not put diſhonour upon them, by diſplacing them, and excluding them from that, for which they have ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved almoſt as long as <hi>Jacob</hi> did for <hi>Rachel,</hi> both in the heat of the day, and coole of the night. As for that deſire, that the Towne of <hi>Lifford</hi> may be the head-quarter. If Sir <hi>Charles Coot,</hi> Lord Preſident, think it convenient, we ſubmit moſt willingly to that Order. As to that part that the three hundred <hi>Engliſh</hi> being at <hi>Lifford,</hi> will be more ready to ſecond the <hi>Engliſh;</hi> It is a moſt pernitious expreſſion proceeding from the ſpirit of contention, and a ſon of <hi>Belial,</hi> which cannot be read nor ſpoken without ſome ſecret horror, by any ingenious or honeſt man, thereby ſecretly importing, that the <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh</hi> are in ſo dangerous a condition, that they needed ſeconding againſt the <hi>Scots,</hi> or as if the <hi>Scots</hi> had a purpoſe to invade them. <hi>O coelum quid ad haec non ſudas, O terra quid non dehiſcis;</hi> Should they who have lived ſo ſweedy together, tyed by many relations, and inviolable bands of amity ſince the firſt Plantation, now neere fifty yeares, confirmed by interchangeable
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:160510:4"/>tyes, bonds of affinity, and ſo mutually engrafted in one anothers affections, that they are become one Tree, though of ſeverall ſtocks. As if they, we ſay, ſhould invade one another, which is as impoſſible (or at leaſt as unlikely) as if a man ſhould be ſo mad, as to teare his own fleſh. For our part, if ever ſuch a day ſhall dawn, we wiſh it may be without perfect light.</p>
               <p>Touching that deſire of the Admiralty of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> which Sir <hi>William Stuart</hi> had during his life-time, that it may be conferred upon my Lord <hi>Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liot.</hi> To this it is anſwered, That Sir <hi>Charles Coot</hi> procured that place to be ſetled on Sir <hi>William Stuart</hi> about three years ſince. And now the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of the Admiralty, having deſigned a Ship of force, and a Pinnace to lye upon the Bay of <hi>Sligo, Balliſhannon, Kilbeggis, Do: Lochſwilly</hi> and <hi>Lochfoyle;</hi> and hath given power to the ſaid Sir <hi>Charles Coot</hi> to command thoſe upon any deſigne for the Parliaments advantage, he having the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand of the Land Forces in thoſe places: The ſaid Committee therefore have thought it moſt convenient for his Lordſhip to have the Admiralty of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> as being moſt proper for him, who hath the command of the Ships, to exerciſe that place, and have reſolved to report it ſo to the Houſe.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="section">
               <head>
                  <hi>September the ninth, 1647.</hi> The Vindication of Captain <hi>John Cunningham,</hi> from the falſe aſperſions caſt upon him by Major <hi>Robert Ormesby,</hi> concerning his Troope, al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledged by <hi>Ormesby,</hi> never to have been raiſed, occaſioned in taking of a Liſt of the Officers name at <hi>Derby-houſe,</hi> the <hi>28.</hi> of <hi>Auguſt</hi> laſt, in Maſter <hi>Froſt</hi> the Secretaries chamber, for a dividend of ſome moneyes to bee given unto the ſeverall Officers towards their journey into <hi>Ireland.</hi>
               </head>
               <p n="1">1. IN Anſwer hereunto, Captain <hi>Cunningham</hi> ſaith, That by vertue of a Commiſſion from Generall Major <hi>Monro,</hi> he did levie a Troope, which attended the <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Army for one whole yeare, in the Province of <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter,</hi> and amongſt other good ſervices done by him, and that Troope a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the bloody <hi>Iriſh</hi> Rebels in the County of <hi>Longford, Cavan, Ard<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>magh,</hi> and <hi>Weſtmeath,</hi> that one dayes ſervice at the bridge of <hi>Fynna</hi> may be ſufficient to equall, yea over-value all the actions done by Major <hi>Ormesby</hi> ſince the day of his birth to this houre.</p>
               <p n="2">2. That the ſaid Troope, by vertue of a Commiſſion from Sir <hi>Charles Coote,</hi> Lord Preſident of <hi>Connaught,</hi> granted unto Captain <hi>Cunningham,</hi> was afterwards brought into the ſervice of that Province.</p>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:160510:5"/>
               <p n="3">3. That it was levied, and tranſported from <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter</hi> thither without pay or levie-money from the State; ſo likewiſe (ſoone after) for want of quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, means, or other encouragement from the Parliament, they diſperſed, as diverſe other Troopes of the like nature did, taken on by Commiſſion from the Lord Preſident, as by his Lordſhips ſpeciall Letters and Certificats may appeare; wherein his Lordſhip moſt nobly engageth himſelf for them to the State, that upon the ſettlement of meanes upon them, theſe Troopes ſo diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved, ſpeedily to being into the Field again, and faithfully to ſerve the State, as formerly they have done.</p>
               <p n="4">4. That this Troope being ſo levied without charge to the State, ſo it diſſolved without any prejudice unot the Army there, or Parliament here, by any unworthy act of Captain <hi>Cunninghams,</hi> or diſhonour unto him whatſoever, which Major <hi>Ormesby</hi> ſo much endevoureth to lay upon him, though this ſame <hi>Ormesby</hi> moſt unworthily loſt his owne Troope, foot Company, and Garriſon, as followeth.</p>
               <p>That in the year 1645. the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Garriſons in the Province of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naught</hi> having taken horſes, and other conſiderable prey by force from the Rebels there; Major <hi>Robert Ormesby</hi> out of which got together about 80. of thoſe plundered horſe, from ſome of our own ſouldiers without charge to him (upon the matter;) good horſes then being ſould for a crowne, or noble the piece, but the moſt part of them he got for nothing. And having procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Commiſſion from Sir <hi>Charles Coot,</hi> Lord Preſident, to command them as a Captain of a Troope of Horſe, was by his Lordſhip liſted and put into pay; which with that Troope and a foot Company (whereof at that time he was only Captain) he was betruſted to keep the Garriſon of <hi>Toulske</hi> in the County of <hi>Roſcomen.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>That by the ſtrength of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Garriſon in that County, they were all put into a very good condition of livelihood, by forcing the <hi>Iriſh</hi> inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants thereabouts into contribution.</p>
               <p>That by this means the ſaid Major <hi>Ormesby</hi> had at leaſt brought into his Garriſon of <hi>Tulske,</hi> fourteen hundred pounds <hi>per annum,</hi> duly paid in mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney, Grain, and other proviſions, by the protected Rebels for the maintenance of his Troopes and foot Company, beſides his ſhare of preyes upon dividend, with the other Garriſons, when they joyned in parties, and marched into the enemies quarters, and beſides great ſtore of corn ſowed in the ground from time to time by the Officers and ſouldiers, and many Families of the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> who came to reſide at the Garriſon of <hi>Tulske,</hi> having in the year 1645, no leſſe corn and proviſion in ſtore, then would have maintained all of them in that Garriſon in a plentifull Condition for a whole yeare.</p>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:160510:5"/>
               <p>That about that time, the Lord Viſcount <hi>Taaffe,</hi> a Rebell, came with a great party of the <hi>Linſter</hi> Rebels, aſſiſted with the Earle of <hi>Clanrickard</hi> and his <hi>Connaught</hi> Rebels, all under the command of the Lord <hi>Taaffe,</hi> au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thorized by Commiſſion from the Lord Marqueſſe of <hi>Ormond,</hi> to fall upon the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Garriſons of that Province, as was alledged, who had not ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to the ceſſation with the Rebles.</p>
               <p>That upon their advance into <hi>Connaught,</hi> they did immediatly fal upon the Garriſon of <hi>Toulske,</hi> in the County of <hi>Roſcomen,</hi> whereof Captain <hi>Robert Ormeſby</hi> (now Major) had the command with his ſaid Foot company and Troope (conſiſting of eighty good horſes) which the ſaid Major kept with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in his Trenches of <hi>Toulske,</hi> and would not be adviſed at a Councell of War by the Lord Preſidents brother, (a gallant Gentleman) Captain <hi>Richard Coot</hi> (now Collonell of Horſe) Sir <hi>George St. George,</hi> Captain <hi>King,</hi> Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain <hi>John Ormeſby,</hi> his Uncle, and other Captains of the ſeverall Garriſons all of them reſolving (if Major <hi>Ormeſby</hi> would joyne with them) to ſtand out in the field with all the Horſe, to annoy the enemy, ſtop their Proviſions, and ſo to preſerve our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Garriſons from being beleagured, but this Major <hi>Ormeſby</hi> would not adhere to their reſolution (though it was the on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly beſt) and told them in plain termes. Gentlemen I have heard you all, but I will follow my own mind; they deſired to know it, but he would not diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover his intentions (which ſoone after to their great griefe was diſcovered) whereupon they departed diſcontented.</p>
               <p>That the Enemie approaching near with great eagerneſſe and reſolution to gain ſo conſiderable a Troope, being aſſured it was in their power to do, ſeeing he kept it within his Trenches, and well knowing Major <hi>Ormeſby</hi> to be a man of as great words as deeds, ſtormed his works and entred, fell in cloſe to the Caſtle-grate (which had a ſtrong Iron-gate on it) where this Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor <hi>Ormeſby</hi> himſelfe was, and might have held it to this day, but he being overcome with puſillanimity and a panick fear, came ſuddenly running out of the Caſtle, calling for mercy, delivered his Piſtoll charged and cocked, to the Rebell Captain <hi>Barnwell,</hi> without either parley or quarter. Much like a ſilly Hare in her thicket, which though ſhee ſeeme to look big, yet with the cry of the Hounds, and noiſe of the hunters, ſhee is ſo terrified, that ſhe runs and knowes not where: So this great Souldier left the ſtrong hold commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted to his charge, from whence he could not be beaten without Cannon; and ran into his enemies armes, where he behaved himſelf with great mode<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie, not ſpeaking a word but mercy, mercy, which Caſtle the Rebels keeps now to the annoyance of the Parliaments Forces in that Province.</p>
               <p>Thus was the conſiderable Garriſon and Caſtle of <hi>Toulske</hi> moſt unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thily
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:160510:6"/>loſt, where the Rebels poſſeſſed themſelves of all Proviſions, Arms, Ammunition, the whole Troop, Foot Company, ſtript both Officer, Sol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dier, and all the Engliſh Families, who were reſiding and had their goods within that place for ſafety: Then the Rebels they carryed this brave <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meſby</hi> along with them upon mercy, whom they might have hanged at their pleaſure, ſeeing he had no quarter, yet ſaved him upon a Deſign to have <hi>Caſtle-Coot</hi> delivered up into their hands, which they conceived might have been effected, by reaſon Major <hi>Ormeſby's</hi> Father and divers of his neereſt Kinſmen were in Caſtle-Coot and had the Command of the place, men, Ammunitions and Proviſions good ſtore. And the ſame, according to their plot, was delivered up to the Rebel Lord <hi>Taaffe,</hi> by Major <hi>Ormeſbys</hi> Father, his Cozen German, Enſign <hi>James Ormeſby</hi> and his brother in Law, (whilſt Major <hi>Ormeſby</hi> himſelf was in the Rebels hands upon mercy:) So that it may be conjectured, and that upon great preſumptions, that the place was delivered meerly to preſerve Major <hi>Ormeſbies</hi> life; It having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merly held out 14. weeks ſiege (being then under the Command of Captain <hi>Richard Coote</hi>) General <hi>Bourke</hi> with 4000. men ſtil battering the ſame with his Ordnance, and was at laſt forced to leave it with the loſs of many of his men. But to return to the matter, the Enemy being much elevated with this good ſucceſs, having got ſo conſiderable a Garriſon as <hi>Toulske,</hi> 80. good Horſes, 100. Foot, all their Arms, one whole years Proviſion, all the Plunder of the Engliſh which they had put into that Garriſon for ſafety.</p>
               <p>That the Rebels forces then drew themſelves immediately before the Town and Caſtle of <hi>Elffynne,</hi> the Biſhops ſeat, and Garriſon of 100. men, which was delivered up to the Enemy; Alſo the walled Town and Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poration of <hi>James-Town,</hi> a Garriſon of one hundred, beſides many Engliſh Inhabitants, yeelded up to the Rebels with divers others of the like manner.</p>
               <p>That all theſe Towns, Caſtles, and Garriſons, Arms, Ammunition, Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, Men and Horſes, might hitherto have been preſerved from the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, if the ſaid Major <hi>Ormesby</hi> had been adviſed by the reſt of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manders of the ſeveral Garriſons before mentioned, eſpecially thoſe who were, by much, his ſuperiors; which not only occaſioned the loſs of theſe conſiderable holds by his wilfulneſs and puſilanimity, but alſo <hi>Caſtle-Coote<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi> the chief houſe of Sir <hi>Charls Coote,</hi> Lord Preſident of that Province, a moſt gallant, active and faithful ſervant of the State, ſo much prejudiced by Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jor <hi>Ormesby</hi> and thoſe of that name, that ſo delivered up <hi>Caſtle-Coote,</hi> (to the great grief of Captain <hi>John Ormeſby</hi> the Majors Unckle, and Lieut<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>Charls Ormeſby</hi> the Majors brother, both wel-deſerving men, who have done very good ſervice) and who merit encouragement from the State,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:160510:6"/>whoſe Father and ſelf were ſervants unto the Lord Preſident and his ever re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nowned father old <hi>S<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Charls Coot,</hi> and made up under them to ſome fortune of Inheritance, and rendred capable by their favor of the place of Juſtice of peace in the Country. And ſince theſe troubles, by Sir <hi>Charls</hi> the Lord Preſidents favor in hopes of better carriage in the ſervice, This <hi>Ormesby</hi> was made Captain and Major of Horſe by his Lordſhips ſeveral Commiſsions.</p>
               <p>Yet ſo ungrateful to his maker is this <hi>Ormesby,</hi> that upon all occaſions he ſtriveth to put particular prejudices, as much as lieth in him, not only on the whole family of the <hi>Cootes,</hi> but alſo upon ſeveral perſons of honor, worth and action, in affinity moſt faithful, near and dear to <hi>Sir Charls Coote,</hi> and moſt zealous in the ſervice of the State, as their ſufferings can wel witneſs. Yet this <hi>Major Ormesby</hi> with a ſeeming ſhew (though in a bold, il-bred, bluſtring way) of agitating for the publick, and therein ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth uſe of <hi>Sir Charls Cootes</hi> name, when on the contrary, nothing is more certain, then the working of his own particular ends, as may evidently ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear by his high and unmerited hopes and demands from the State. And the ſaid <hi>Ormesby,</hi> by the former loſſes aforeſaid, occaſioned alſo the loſs of the Abbey of <hi>Boyle,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Kings</hi> houſe, the Fort of <hi>Carrickdrumcouske</hi> belonging to Sir <hi>George Liſedoorne, Knockevicker,</hi> with many other holds, and conſequently the <hi>whole Province of Connaught;</hi> But what ſince thereof hath been regained by <hi>Sir Charls Coote</hi> Lord Preſident, with the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments Forces</hi> under his command, ſince his <hi>Government there.</hi> All which may <hi>moſt evidently appear</hi> againſt <hi>Major Ormesby,</hi> if queſtioned at a <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cel of War</hi> in that Kingdom <hi>before the Lord Preſident, at once</hi> with Lieut. <hi>Roukesby</hi> (to which <hi>purpoſe</hi> it is deſired <hi>that the</hi> ſaid <hi>Ormesbies</hi> perſon be <hi>ſecured here</hi> and <hi>he ſent over</hi>) which <hi>Roukesby,</hi> who is apprehended in this City, and is by Order of <hi>the Houſe to be ſent over to</hi> Sir <hi>Charls Coote</hi> to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bide tryal <hi>for his betraying and delivering up of</hi> James-<hi>Town afore-menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned, with other matters there to be laid to Major</hi> Ormesby's <hi>charge con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the laſt defeat given by the Rebels to our</hi> Connaught <hi>horſe, neer the Caſtle of</hi> Roſcomen, <hi>wherein he was Actor.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Yet notwithſtanding all which apparent agreat prejudice done to the Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament, by the loſs of a Province occaſioned by Major</hi> Robert Ormesby <hi>as aforeſaid, put many good Engliſh Proteſtant Families a begging in this Kingdom,</hi> and many in that Kingdom, who <hi>have not wherewithal</hi> to carry them <hi>hither to be relieved; the</hi> loſs of ſo <hi>conſiderable a Troop, Foot Company, Gariſon,</hi> and <hi>plentiful Quarters, Arms, Ammunition</hi> and <hi>Proviſions</hi> in the <hi>ſeveral ſtores,</hi> which wil coſt the <hi>Parliament grat</hi> ſumme of <hi>money, beſides the loſs</hi> of many Engliſh men <hi>before thoſe</hi> holds and Province
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:160510:7"/>can <hi>bee regained,</hi> which by his <hi>meanes meerely</hi> have beene loſt. And his own quarters being unworthily loſt, as we before related, hee came with his wife, father and family, to the Lagan, where he was ſcarcely well ſetled, till he and his father began to pry into the ſecrets of the country, and look for Cuſtodiums, as if the ſeverall Collonels and Officers who had fought for the preſervation of that country had deſerved none, but al been hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto reſerved for him who lived an hundred miles from thence in another Province; and by importunity procured a <hi>Cuſtodium</hi> from Sir <hi>John Clot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>worthy,</hi> and Sir <hi>Robert Merideth</hi> of <hi>Caſtle Bliaen,</hi> and of ſix quarters of land, which entertaines eight ſcore ſouldiers, which after the rate of fifteene pence a week, amounteth to five hundred and twenty pound a year, for ten pound to be accompted to the State, which will put him in a condition thriſe ſo good as ever he was in his life before; beſide his employment, having a Troope of Horſe, being Major of a Regiment and a foot Company, when hundreds of better men then he &amp; morefaithful to the State, have not bread to put in their mouths, or to cover their nakedneſſe; neither theſe eight ſcore Souldiers who have faithfully ſerved in many bloody battels againſt the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bels, have not any means to releeve them, if this <hi>Ormesby</hi> take away their quarter upon any pretext whatſoever.</p>
               <p>That Major <hi>Ormesby</hi> nevertheleſſe, as if no ſuch matter had ever been done by him, applyes himſelf to the Parliament here, with impudence and bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
               <p>Firſt, importunatly deſiring from my Lord <hi>Lile,</hi> then Lord Lieutenant of <hi>Ireland,</hi> a Commiſſion, to command a Regiment of Horſe, made up of the ſeveral Troopes raiſed and armed in the beginning of the rebellion, by my Lord <hi>Cleandeboys,</hi> Sir <hi>William Stewart,</hi> Sir <hi>Robert Stewart,</hi> and Sir <hi>Willi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am Col,</hi> without the which Troopes to attend the Regiments, they would be almoſt unprofitable. This deſire his Lordſhip moſt prudently put off to the determination of a Councell of War, as being unwilling to diſcourage him, being a ſtranger, but his Lordſhip (by the adviſe of the ſaid Councell of War holden in <hi>Salisſbury</hi> Houſe) found it dangerous to grant that requeſt, which might prove prejudiciall to the ſervice, by giving an <hi>Iriſh</hi> man, bred in the moſt remote and barbarous parts of <hi>Ireland,</hi> the command of ſo many men of Honour, all of them being Collonels, one of them a Lord Viſcount, the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther three Knights, and ſome of theſe Privy Councellours and Barronets.</p>
               <p>And ſecondly, He likewiſe Petitions the Committee of Star-Chamber, ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth how that his Father and he had disburſed 4000 <abbr>l.</abbr> in the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſervice, and in raiſing, arming, clothing and maintaining of that Foot
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:160510:7"/>Company and Troop of Horſe, procures Certificates on his behalf, gets an Order of that Committee for a Report to be made in the Houſe for this 4000 <abbr>l.</abbr> to be granted unto him, demands a new Troop for himſelf, and the Command of a Regiment of Horſe, and aims at greater matters with as much confidence as if he had left both Troop and Company in the ſervice, nor never had the ſaid 1400 <abbr>l.</abbr> 
                  <hi>per annum</hi> out of his quarters of <hi>Toulske</hi> for maintaining and clothing of them.</p>
               <p>Let therefore the premiſes and particulars herein contained be taken in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſerious conſideration by all wel-affected people, whether Major <hi>Robert Ormesby</hi> doth deſerve the granting of this 4000 <abbr>l.</abbr> unto him by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, or ſuch additions of greater imployments to be conferred upon him, until he be firſt tryed and cleared at a Councel of War for the ſame, or ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to his demerits puniſhed, to the terror of others to commit the like hereafter.</p>
               <p>For if ſuch incouragements ſhould be conferred upon men ſo highly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>judiciall to the State, and others who have been lately here having faithfully ſerved them, and been very fortunate bygiving many great defeats and over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throwes to the Rebells, without the leaſt ſpot or diſhonour whatſoever, and have ſuffered extreamly in their eſtates, deeply ingaged in ſeverall ſums of money, for raiſing and arming of their ſeverall Regiments, Troops, and Companies, who have humbly Petitioned the State to be releeved of their engagements, having exhauſted themſelves by long attendance, in which time ſome of them were Arreſted for the engagements of the State, others for old demands before theſe troubles, and could neither procure their per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons protected, releived, nor any part of their Arrears given unto them whereby to ſubſiſt. Notwithſtanding they never had any pay from the State ſix years, but three moneths means in commodities. That above forty of thoſe Officers of Ireland had onely of late about 300. <abbr>l.</abbr> divided amongſt them to carry them away, ſome of them having attended the State here above 15 moneths, others a leſſer time. Then let the world judge what ſuch who have ſerved faithfully and have not received any manner of encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ragement from the State ſhal think, when this Major <hi>Ormsby</hi> who hath done them ſo great diſ-ſervice ſhall receive the 4000. <abbr>l.</abbr> he is now a Petitioner for, and great imployments conferred upon him, and who hath received as much as any one of thoſe Officers upon this dividend of the 300. <abbr>l.</abbr> to carry him into Ireland and yet not gone, beſides 100. <abbr>l.</abbr> in ready money which he received at his comming over.</p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="articles">
            <pb n="14" facs="tcp:160510:8"/>
            <head>Articles whereupon Major Ormesby is to be tryed at a Councell of War.</head>
            <p n="1">
               <hi>1</hi> WHether or no did the ſaid Major in June <hi>1645</hi> (he being beſt acquainted in Connaught) vvhen the Brittiſh in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>lſter vvent thither, go along with thoſe Forces, and was he not uſed as a guide through Connaught to the Caſtle of Shrewl? did not the ſaid Major hinder the Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh &amp; Scots who reſolved to fight the Rebels being drawn up in their vvay, And did he not alleadge, That thoſe Rebels vvere the Earl of Glanrikards friends and Kinſmen, vvho had not then declared himſelf in a hoſtile vvay? And for the truth hereof let Collonel <hi>Conway</hi> vvitneſs, Sir <hi>James Mount<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gomery,</hi> Captain <hi>Anteill,</hi> Captain <hi>Kilner,</hi> and many other Officers both Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh and Scots, vvho vvere onely ſtrangers in that Province, and directed by the ſaid Major. Yet nevertheleſs the <hi>Britiſh</hi> vvere reproachfully bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded vvith that neglect vvhereof he vvas the cauſe, meerly to ſave ſome of his Country men and acquaintance, neighbours and Kinſmen, he, his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther and Anceſtors living amongſt them, and allyed to them by many gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, and whoſe Eſtate, if he have any, is amongſt them yet in that Province?</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Whether or no the ſaid Major by his Covvardize rendred himſelf Priſoner to Captain <hi>Barnwell</hi> in his ovvn Trench, and ſo baſely loſt a Troop of good horſe, though they coſt him nothing, a Foot Company vvhich ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tred themſelves in Tulske, and all the goods belonging to the Engliſh there, and in Generall did not the ſaid Major occaſion all the loſſe?</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Did not the ſaid Major occaſion the loſſe of Caſtle Coote, vvherein his Father and ſome of his friends vvere chief Commanders, to ſave his life, vvho ſubmitted himſelf to the mercy of the Rebels without Quarter, and might have hanged him when they pleaſed.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> Did not the ſaid <hi>Ormsby</hi> loſe the battell of <hi>Roſcomen,</hi> by giving a vvrong vvord, and flying himſelf firſt, and vvas never ſeen for <hi>10</hi> or <hi>12</hi> miles, vvhen as others vvhom he blames and calumniatess, kirmiſhed all the time in the Reer, receicing the charges of the Enemy till the ſpent horſe vvere gone and recovered breath: And in this manner moſt of the Officers behaved themſelves in a body near <hi>20</hi> miles together, but he vvas never ſeen, alledging that he vvas ſhot through the Arme, vvhen a Bullet onely grazed on him, as by the skar may yet be ſeen, his bones being all vvhole?</p>
         </div>
         <div type="queries">
            <pb n="15" facs="tcp:160510:8"/>
            <head>Queries to be put to Major Ormesby by the Lord Preſident of Connaugh concerning the 4000. <abbr>l.</abbr> he Petitions the Parliament for.</head>
            <p n="1">1 <hi>WHere this</hi> 4000. <abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>was in the time of peace, it not being known to his neighbours that he was worth</hi> 100. <abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>of ready money?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>When gave he out this money for the Parliaments <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>By whoſe Direction was it and who undertook to pay him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>For what commodities to the Parliaments uſe was that money disburſed and which way could the Parliament be bettered</hi> 4000. <abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>by him?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>What is become of thoſe penniworths, and who diſpoſed of them or made uſe of them to the Parliaments advantage; For if a Merchant give an account he muſt ſet down a liſt of the Commodities, and who received them, when and where, the day of the moneth, and year of God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Why did the ſaid Major preſume to miſ-informe men of honour, quality, and known integrity, who could not be privie to all his Actions in procu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring a certificate from them, which certificate he uſes as a principall ground to ſtrengthen his Petition for the ſaid</hi> 4000. <abbr>l.</abbr> 
               <hi>Which is to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ported to the houſe of Commons; And alſo under colour of that certificate be aſſumes the glory of the ſervices; performed in Conaught, to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, when as others far more deſerving are paſt by with ſilence.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now, if Major <hi>Ormesby</hi> ſhall paſſe free, notwithſtanding what can be ſaid againſt him, or be rewarded for doing nothing, It will be far more favour then the L. <hi>Moore,</hi> L. <hi>Convvay,</hi> Lord <hi>Chicheſter, Claneboyes</hi> or <hi>Ards,</hi> have had, though all Noblemen: and any of them have ſuffered more by the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, &amp; disburſed more then he &amp; al his generation are worth: yet al of them either want their Regiments, poſſeſſion of their Eſtates, or their perſons lye in Captivity many moneths for their ſervice to the Parliament; And yet their Petitions, it read, be not granted. But indeed this brave <hi>Ormsby</hi> takes a better courſe then any of thoſe Noblemen to atchieve his ends, for he is of every Nation and every profeſſion as may beſt ſerve his turn. Amongſt the Presbyterians he is Presbyterian, amongſt the Independents he is an Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent, amongſt the Iriſh he is an Iriſhman, and that is true indeed; amongſt the Engliſh he is an Engliſhman, if he were not betrayed by his Iriſh accent and breeding; and amongſt the Scots, <hi>if his God dam-me</hi> may be taken, he loves them above all the world. And for his valour, if you beleeve his own
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:160510:9"/>report, it is above that of <hi>Achilles</hi> and his <hi>Mirmidones</hi> whereof he had a great purpoſe to have given ſufficient proof with the <hi>Venetians</hi> againſt the <hi>Turks,</hi> had he not been informed that Prince <hi>Rupert</hi> was to be Generall of their Army, who hath conceived ſuch indignation againſt Major <hi>Ormsby</hi> (as himſelf reports) That the Prince hath vowed he never ſhall have quarter if he get him in a field: and the reaſon is, the name of Major <hi>Ormsby</hi> ſtrook ſuch terror in the Iriſh, that they durſt not ſend over the ten thouſand they promiſed the King, for fear of him, leaſt he had deſtroyed the whole King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Ireland in their abſence. And to conclude, it may appear by this preceding diſcourſe, that this man lies aming at great promotion, great ſums of money, but as yet he is onely poſſeſt by hope; howſoever he deſerves this Epitaph.</p>
            <q>
               <l>Here lyes the luſty <hi>Phaeton,</hi> which took in hand to guide,</l>
               <l>His Fathers Chariot, from the which although he chanc'd to ſlide,</l>
               <l>Yet that he gave a proud at tempt, it cannot be denied.</l>
            </q>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
